Anastasis Kratsios

Geometric Deep Learning and Foundations of Data Science

University of Basel Department of Mathematics and Computer Science Spiegelgasse 1 4051 Basel Switzerland (a) (+41) 78 933 99 19

Profile

Specialization: I develop and study universal deep learning models capable of leveraging complicated geometric structures in data science and stochastic analysis.

Expertise (Mathematics): Approximation theory, mathematical finance, geometric topology, optimal transport, analysis on metric spaces.

Expertise (Data Science): Geometric deep learning, deep learning, meta-learning. Select Research:

- NEU: A Meta-Algorithm for Universal UAP-Invariant Feature Representation (JMLR) The Journal of Machine Learning Research, 2021.
- Non-Euclidean Universal Approximation (NeurIPS) Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems, 2020.
- Universal Approximation Under Constraints is Possible with Transformers ArXiV: 2110.03303.

Employment History

Academic

2021-Current Postdoctoral Researcher - Geometric Deep Learning, University of Basel, Basel. Switzerland.

- Achievements: "Universal approximation under constraints is possible with transformers":
 - ICRL 2022 (#1 ML Conference, H-score 253) submission: ranked in the top 0.05% in the current (first) round.
 - ICRL 2022 submission received one of the only 39 total 10/10s awarded out of the total ≈ 3400 submissions.
- Select Contributions:
 - First neural network architecture capable of universal approximation with exact constraint satisfaction,
 - First deep neural version of Berge's Maximum Theorem (1963) with exact constraint satisfaction.
- o Co-supervision: Doctoral Student T. Liu
 - Completed Collaboration (Numerical Part): Universal Approximation under constraints is possible with transformers,
 - Working Paper: Generalization bounds for random feature models between Banach, supporting Schauder basises, when data-generating distribution is supported on an unknown manifold,
- Ongoing Research Projects:
 - Adapted universal approximation of stochastic processes by recurrent transformer networks - B. Acciaio and G. Pammer (ETH Math. Finance) - Expected Dec. 1^{rst},
 - PAC-Bayesian Bounds in Function Space P. Kassraie and J. Rothfuss (ETH Comp. Sci.) - Expected January 15^{th} .
 - Canonical Quantitative Universal Approximators for General Metric Spaces M. Lassas (U. Helsinki), M. de Hoop (Rice U.) - Expected March 1^{rst} ,
 - Regret-Optimal Stochastic Gradient Descent Algorithms G. Livieri (S. Normale Superior, Pisa), P. Casgrain (ETH Zürich) - Expected TBA.

2018-2021 Postdoctoral Researcher - Stochastic Finance and Geometric Deep Learning,

ETH Zürich, Zürich, Switzerland

- Select contributions:
 - Introduced the first (quantitative) universal approximation theorems for general inputoutput spaces,
 - Developed the first universal approximator from the space of Gaussian measures with Wasserstein metric, to itself,
 - Developed the first meta-optimization procedure for learning regret-optimal gradientdescent algorithms,
 - Developed the first penalty for arbitrage-free machine learning in finance,
 - Proved first deterministic universal classification theorems,
 - Introduce meta-algorithm for generating optimal UAP-invariant feature maps,
 - Developed an architecture capable of uniformly approximating discontinuous functions,
 - Obtained the first characterization of the universal approximation property.
- Supervision:
 - Guide: L. Papon (Master's Student from EPFL),
 - Master's Semester Project: An Overview of Risk-Averse Valuation.
 - Student: Nikolaos Mourdoukoutas.

2014-2015 **Lecturer**, *Concordia University*, Montreal, Canada.

- Transferred my intuition to new students in the field,
- Framed classical theory in the context of modern applications; such as data-science examples to motivate linear algebraic ideas,
- Provided extended lectures outside of requirements to help students go beyond their requirements and succeed in their exams.

Private Sector

2017 Risk Management Research, CIBC Capital Markets, Toronto, Canada

- Modelled for non-modellable risk-factors for the FRTB under Basel III,
- Developed clustering based model selection methodology for liquid bonds proxying,
- Part of the team working on stochastic filtering-based methods for predicting IPO prices.
- Developed algorithms for Bloomberg to R interphasing.

Outreach

2016–2017 Mathematics Educator for Students with Learning Disabilities, *Epsilon Learning Center*, Toronto (Leslieville), Canada.

- Tutored 6-13 year old students with learning disabilities,
- Help to discover and overcome each student's learning barriers,
- Identified personalized learning tools (e.g. visual, analytic, mechanical, etc..) helping each student best connect to the material,
- Helped build student's "mathematical self-confidence".

Education

2014–2018 PhD Mathematical Finance, Concordia University, Montreal

- Thesis: Arbitrage-free Regularization, Geometric Learning, And Non-Euclidean Filtering In Finance.
- Contributions:
 - Developed the NEU meta-algorithm, a procedure which learns an optimal loss function given a learning task and a data-set,
 - Applied the NEU meta-algorithm to stock prediction and yield-curve dimensionality reduction tasks,

- Introduced no-arbitrage penalty in the generalized HJM framework and used it to learn arbitrage-free forward-rate curve models,
- Introduced a non-Euclidean filtering algorithm for Cartan-Hadamard spaces and used it to predict efficient portfolios.
- Research Groups: Quantact and Montreal Analysis Seminar.

2012–2014 MSc Pure Mathematics, University of Montreal, Montreal

- Thesis: Bounding The Hochschild Cohomological Dimension
- Major Contributions:
 - Developed a lower-bound on the Hochschild cohomological dimension for any K-algebra,
 - Used this lower-bound to show that most commutative K-algebras fail to be smooth.
- Research Groups: CIRGET, Graduate Students Seminar in Mathematics.

2009–2012 BA Pure and Applied Mathematics, Concordia University, Montreal.

Research Articles

Publications

- 2021 **NEU: A Meta-Algorithm for Universal UAP-Invariant Feature Representa- tion**, (JMLR) The Journal of Machine Learning Research.

 Joint work with: C. Hyndman
- 2021 Optimizing Optimizers: Regret-optimal gradient descent algorithms, (COLT) 34^{th} Conference on Learning Theory. Joint work with: P. Casgrain
- 2021 **The Universal Approximation Property**, Annals of Mathematics and Artificial Intelligence.
- 2020 **Non-Euclidean Universal Approximation**, (NeurlPS) 33^{th} Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems.

Joint work with: I. Bilokopytov

- 2020 **Arbitrage-Free Regularization**, Risks Special Issue on Machine Learning in Finance, Insurance and Risk Management.

 Joint work with: C. Hyndman
- 2020 **The Entropic Measure Transform**, Canadian Journal of Statistics Special Issue: Special Issue on Stochastic Models, Statistics, and Finance.

 Joint work with: C. Hyndman and R. Wang
- 2021 Lower-Estimates on the Hochschild (Co)Homological Dimension of Commutative Algebras and Applications to Smooth Affine Schemes and Quasi-Free Algebras, Mathematics Special Issue: New Trends in Algebraic Geometry and Its Applications.

Under Review

2021 Universal Approximation Under Constraints is Possible with Transformers, *ArXiV*: 2110.03303.

Joint work with: I. Dokmanic, T. Liu, and B. Zamanlooy

2021 Universal Approximation Theorems for Geometric Deep Learning, *ArXiV*: 2101.05390.

Joint work with: L. Papon

- 2021 Universal Regular Conditional Distributions via Probability Measure-Valued Deep Neural Models, *ArXiV*: 2105.07743.
- 2021 Learning Sub-Patterns in Piece-Wise Continuous Functions, *ArXiV*: 2010.15571.

Joint work with: B. Zamanlooy

- 2021 Denise: Deep Robust Principal Component Analysis for Positive Semidefinite Matrices, ArXiV: 2004.13612.
 Joint work with: J. Teichmann, P. Ruyssen, C. Herrera, and F. Krach
- 2021 A Canonical Transform for Strengthening the Local L^p -Type Universal Approximation Property, ArXiV: 2006.14378.

Joint work with: B. Zamanlooy

White Papers

- 2017 **Replication of a Real-Estate Market Index (Teranet)**, Proceedings: Proceedings: Eighth Montreal Industrial Problem Solving Workshop.
- 2014 Hochschild Cohomological Dimension is Not Upper Semi-Continuous, *Note. ArXiV: 1407.4825.*

Conferences and Talks

- 2021 **Generic Geometric Priors via Probabilistic Transformers**, *Rice University's: MATH+X Symposium*, Costra Rica, Costra Rica
- 2022 **Regular Conditional Distributions via Probabilistic Transformers**, *Bachelier Colloquium*, Metabief, Metabief, France
- 2021 Universal Approximation with Exact Constraint Satisfaction is Possible with Transformers, *TU Munich*, Munich, Germany
- 2021 Geometric Deep Learning for High-Dimensional Option Pricing and Constrained Approximation, AIMS Lab Seminar, McMaster University, Hamilton, Canada
- 2021 Universal Approximation with Exact Constraint Satisfaction is Possible with Transformers, Talks in Financial and Insurance Mathematics, ETH Zürich
- 2021 **Universal Probability Measure-Valued Deep Neural Networks**, *Probability Days*, University of Mannheim (Remote)
- 2021 Optimizing Optimizers: Regret-optimal gradient descent algorithms, *COLT* 2021, Boulder, Colorado (Remote)
- 2021 **Quantitative Non-Euclidean Universal Approximation**, *ML Explained Aggregate Intellect Al.Science*, Online, Toronto, Canada (Remote)

- 2021 Universal Probability Measure-Valued Deep Neural Networks , Quantact (CRM), Montreal, Canada,
- 2020 Non-Euclidean Universal Approximation, 34th NeurIPS 2020, Online, NA
- 2020 Universal Feature Map Generation, ETH Zürich, Zürich, Switzerland
- 2020 Limit Orderbook Geometry and Arbitrage-Free Volume Adjustments, Imperial College, London, United Kingdom Invited by: Damiano Brigo
- 2019 **NEU Meta-Learning, Universal Approximation Properties, and Learning Model-Free Loss-Functions**, *ETH Zürich*, Zürich, Switzerland
- 2019 **Universal Approximation Theorems**, *Concordia Data Science Seminar*, Montreal, Canada.
- 2019 **A Universal Feature Space** , *12th Freiburg-Wien-Zürich (FWZ) Seminar*, Zürich, Switzerland.
- 2019 **Universal Approximation Theorems**, Österreichische Mathematische Gesellschaft Conference 2019, Dornbirn, Austria.
- 2019 **Universal Approximation Theorems**, *Vienna Congress on Mathematical Finance VCMF 2019*, Vienna, Austria.
- 2019 **Arbitrage-Free Regularization**, 10th Freiburg-Wien-Zürich (FWZ) Seminar, Vienne, Autstria.
- 2019 Risk-Averse Conditional Expectation and Shortfall-Regression, ETH Zürich, Zürich, Switzerland.
- 2018 Geometric Learning and Filtering in Finance , 10^{th} Bachelier World Congres, Dublin, Ireland.
- 2018 Arbitrage-Free Regularization, 10^{th} Bachelier World Congres, Dublin, Ireland.
- 2018 **Arbitrage-Free Regularization**, 5^{th} Workshop on Insurance Mathematics with a Special Session on Big-Data and Machine Learning in Risk Management , Montreal, Canada.
- 2017 A Geometric Approach to Arbitrage-Free Modeling, Estimation, and Prediction, International Conference on Mathematical Finance, Waterloo, Canada. Presentation by coauthor.
- 2017 **Geometric Learning and Non-Euclidean Filtering in Finance**, Canadian Mathematical Society Winter Meeting, Waterloo, Canada.
- 2017 A Geometric Approach to Arbitrage-Free Modeling, Estimation, and Prediction, 11^{th} Bachelier Colloquium on Mathematical Finance and Stochastic Calculus, Métabief, France.

 Presentation by coauthor.

- 2016 Manifold Learning Algorithms for Arbitrage-Free Low-Dimensional on-Linear Model Selection, Pacific Institute for the Mathematical Sciences (PIMS); High-Frequency Trading Workshop, Edmonton, Canada.
- 2016 A Geometric Approach to Arbitrage-Free Modeling, Estimation, and Prediction, Canadian Mathematical Society Winter Meeting, Niagra, Canada. Presentation by coauthor.
- 2016 Manifold learning algorithms for arbitrage-free low-dimensional nonlinear model selection, AMS AMS Fall Meeting, Brunswick, USA.

 Presentation by coauthor.
- 2016 **Arbitrage-Free Regularization for Forward Rates**, *ENCS Data Science Research Centre*, Montreal, Canada.

Extracurricular Activities

Academic Community

- 2018–present **Weekly Geometric Deep Learning Seminar**, *University of Basel*, Basel, Switzerland.
 - \circ Give feedback and guide 3^{rd} of PhD students in same area,
 - Invite Speakers and possible group collaborators,
 - Organize seminar.
 - 2018–2021 **Organiser of the Weekly Financial and Insurance Mathematics Seminar**, *ETH Zürich*, Zürich, Switzerland.
 - o Organize the weekly seminar,
 - Align schedules with international researchers,
 - Author the weekly news bulletin.
 - 2017–2018 Vice-President Mathematics and Statistics Graduate Students Association, Concordia University, Montreal, Canada.
 - Organised student social events and outings,
 - Helped maintain graduate student's positive morale by introducing a free coffee system.